Guide to the Underwood Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Underwood family papers
1860-1939
MS 1173
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
(1 box, 1 folio)
Principal figures in these papers are Clara A. Case Underwood, her daughter, Clara Beatrice, and son, Eugene Bertrand. Included is some family correspondence (1860-1904), an autograph album kept by Clara A. Underwood, European travel diaries and notes written by Clara Beatrice Underwood (1903), and various certificates of membership and diplomas of Eugene Bertrand Underwood and his first wife, Lottie Elizabeth Treat Underwood.
Underwood family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Eugene B. Underwood, 1940-1948, and Mr. Ray Sanborn, 1947.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Underwood Family Papers concern Judson B. Underwood, his wife, Clara A. Case, their daughter Clara Beatrice Underwood, their son Eugene Bertrand Underwood, and the latter's wife, Lottie Elizabeth Treat. The papers include seven letters to family members, typed transcripts of travel journals, an autograph album, and assorted diplomas and certificates. In the correspondence are one letter each from Henry W. Farnam, Arthur T. Hadley, and Andrew Phillips to Clara B. Underwood, secretary in the Yale University Graduate School.
These papers were donated to Yale University by Eugene B. Underwood between 1940 and 1948, and by M. Ray Sanborn in 1947.
Biographical / Historical
Eugene Bertrand Underwood, 1873-1960
In the engineering and contracting business; address, Box 1322, New Haven, Conn.
Residence, "Pinoak," Rimmon Road, Woodbridge, Conn.
Underwood has been engaged in the electrical business under his own name for some years. From 1907 to 1917 he was also president of the Brown & Underwood Automobile Company, distributors of Cadillac cars for New Haven County. He was at one time with the General Electric Company in Schenectady and Lynn, and he has also been connected with the electrical department of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad.
Underwood is a Baptist. He served as secretary of the Yale Alumni Association of New Haven from its organization in 1909 until 1926, and from 1920 to 1926 he was also its treasurer. Since 1926 he has been a vice-president of the organization, in charge of scholarship matters. Underwood served in the Connecticut State Guard from December 6, 1917 to May 13, 1921. During the next nine months he was a Private in the Connecticut National Guard.
Underwood has been married twice, his first marriage taking place in New Haven, May 25, 1899, to Lottie Elizabeth Treat, daughter of George A. and Emma C. (Hine) Treat. They had two children, Bertrand, who was born April 12, 1903, and died May 17, 1903, and Charlotte, who was born and died March 20, 1905. Mrs. Underwood's death occurred in Woodbridge, on March 16, 1923. In September, 1923, Underwood was married to Katherine Irene Kelly, of New Haven.
From Thirty-Year Record of the Class of 1896, Sheffield Scientific School, Yale University, 1928.
Families; Europe -- Description and travel; Autographs; Diaries; Underwood, Clara Beatrice; Underwood, Clare A. Case; Underwood, Eugene Bertrand, 1873-1960; Underwood, Lottie Elizabeth Treat, d. 1923; Underwood family
- Inventory, 1860-1939
  - Family Correspondence, 1860-1904 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clara A. (Case) Underwood: autograph album, 1862-1876 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clara B. Underwood
    - European travel notes, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 3 - 4)
    - "Notes of Our Tour 1903" for Louise Richards, with cover letter (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Trip to Italy and Greece, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "The Amateur Traveler, or, In Search of Ferny Hallways," sent to Clara B. Underwood by Margery Bailey, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Passport, 1914 June 30 (Box 2)
  - Eugene Bertrand Underwood
    - Chautauqua Reading Union certificate, 1888-1889 (Box 2)
    - Washington School certificate, 1889 April 20 (Box 2)
    - New Haven High School diploma, 1893 April 25 (Box 2)
    - Military Certificate, Sheffield Scientific School, Yale University, 1896 June 10 (Box 2)
    - Connecticut State Guard, appointment as Sergeant in sanitary detachment, 1919 May 17 (Box 2)
    - Connecticut State Guard, discharge, 1921 May 13 (Box 2)
    - Connecticut National Guard, discharge, 1922 February 7 (Box 2)
  - J. B. Underwood: Grand Lodge Knights of Pythias of Connecticut certificate, 1882 July 24 (Box 2)
  - Lottie Elizabeth (Treat) Underwood
    - New Haven High School diploma, 1892 April 28 (Box 2)
    - Welch Training School for Teachers certificate, 1893 June 30 (Box 2)
    - Chautauqua Literary and Scientific Circle certificate, 1897 August 18 (Box 2)
    - Daughters of the American Revolution application, 1911 April 17 (Box 2)
    - Daughters of the American Revolution certificate, 1911 September 23 (Box 2)
  - Henry C. Morse: appointment to Masonic degree of Royal Arch Mason, 1861 October 8 (Box 2)
  - Map of the Yale Engineering Camp, 1934 (Box 2)